<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.2 20190208//EN"
                  "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd">
<article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" dtd-version="1.2" article-type="other">
<front>
<journal-meta>
<journal-id></journal-id>
<journal-title-group>
</journal-title-group>
<issn></issn>
<publisher>
<publisher-name></publisher-name>
</publisher>
</journal-meta>
<article-meta>
<permissions>
</permissions>
</article-meta>
</front>
<body>
<disp-quote>
  <p>Memristive STDP Synapses and Unsupervised Learning</p>
  <p>Tabeeb Rahman, Bsc Mathematics and Physics, Department of Physics,
  University of Bath, Bath UK</p>
</disp-quote>
<p><bold><italic>Abstract</italic>—In the field of machine learning,
Artificial Neural Networks (ANNs of the generalised perceptron type [1])
model synapses as scalars (for a generic synaptic strength variable),
and typically relies on updating the value of the synapse (synaptic
plasticity) in a globally coordinated (synchronous), iterative process
(Gradient Descent [2]) to train the model. In the currently prevalent
Von Neumann computer hardware paradigm, such computations are energy
expensive. Motivated by the energy efficiency of biological brains, the
spike-timing-dependent plasticity (STDP) rule supposes synaptic
plasticity be modelled asynchronously for a biologically inspired
autonomous synapse, with strength change dependent on the relative spike
timing between a pair of connected biologically inspired spiking
neurons. These neurons differ from fixed scalar representations of
neurons in ANNs by emitting discrete voltage spikes when sufficiently
stimulated, and networks of such are called Spiking Neural Networks
(SNNs).</bold></p>
<p><bold>This project computationally simulated the AIST (Ag-In-Sb-Te)
memristor to investigate the claim that it can act as an artificial STDP
synapse to support learning inside of an SNN. Memristors are compact
resistive devices that can have their conductances (storing the STDP
synaptic strength variable) pro­grammed with external voltages, known as
pulse programming. A pair of spiking-type neurons were situated pre- and
post- strongly, with</bold> 1 −|𝑟| <bold>(Pearson’s r) found to be on
the order</bold></p>
<p><bold>reproduction. These non-idealities were not used in the AIST
simulation model for simplicity. For this reason, hardware
im­plementations of large memristive SNNs remain elusive.</bold></p>
<p><bold>The project also assessed the claim that the STDP rule is
sufficient to effectively train SNNs with unlabelled training data
(unsupervised learning). A full-scale ideal STDP SNN with</bold></p>
<p><bold>claim, though falls short of the 99</bold>%<bold>+ accuracy of
Gradient</bold> I. Introduction</p>
<disp-quote>
  <p>Biological neural systems continue to motivate the search</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>for more energy-efficient Machine learning approaches. Many</p>
<p>conventional machine learning methods including Gradient</p>
<p>Descent are made to run iterative plasticity updates that</p>
<p>require global coordination with the rest of the network, in</p>
<p>order to adhere to the in order (serial) nature of the Von</p>
<p>Neumann computational paradigm that most computers since</p>
<p>the dawn of the transistor age uses. The bottlenecks found in</p>
<p>the Von Neumann architecture is fundamental to its synchrony</p>
<disp-quote>
  <p>and serial command execution nature. Iterations must be
  synchronised and carried out serially. Results of prior itera­tions are
  shuttled serially to and from the place where results are physically
  stored (memory) to the circuits responsible for mathematical
  computation and program execution, via serial data buss circuits. Each
  result in an iterative approach relies on the accuracy of prior
  results, so the signal integrity needed over these data busses is
  high. Additionally, larger networks require more data to be shuttled
  and synchronised over these serial busses than current data busses can
  handle. This Von neumann Bottleneck is fundamental to machine learning
  tasks, since in the context of neural networks, they are represented
  by graphs of edge (representing the synapse and associated strength)
  connected nodes (neurons). In densely connected graphs adding nodes
  makes the number of synapses grow quadratically, whereas scaling data
  throughput through serial data busses demands exponentially higher
  signal-to-noise ratios [3], requiring an increase in the number of
  more inefficient higher accuracy signal amplifiers. Also, Gradient
  Descent allows for synaptic updates to be done independently of one
  another (in parallel) on a proper subset of neurons and synapses at
  once, with each set being called a layer of neurons. Doing layer level
  computations simultaneously is poorly suited for the serial nature of
  these data busses, and is hard to scale for layers with more neurons
  in them. Adding more busses in parallel only grows the data throughput
  linearly but is prohibitively expensive to manufacture since adding
  more data busses takes up die space on silicon wafers, that would
  otherwise have been populated with mathematical logic circuits.</p>
  <p>By contrast, biological brains are thought to implement synaptic
  plasticity by autonomous self-updating synapses acting locally on
  themselves, allowing for parallel computa­tion at a per neuron-pair
  synapse level, vastly increasing the scalability of neural
  computations compared to Von Neumann based Gradient Descent
  approaches. Biological brains are also far more noise tolerant, with
  each synapse in, for example a human brain existing in a very noisy
  environment. Humans still consistently outperform state of the art
  Reasoning Lan­guage models [4] whilst consuming just 20 Watts of power
  [5]. The high noise tolerance and parallel native architecture of
  human and biological brains are thought to be primarily responsible
  for the currently inaccessible task-performance per watt capabilities
  they possess. This is the primary motivation for research into
  neuromorphic (inspired by neuroscience) hardware.</p>
  <p>For the purposes of the SNN section and the pulse program­ming used
  in Memristive STDP synapse simulations, Various biological neuron
  models were researched. Hodgkin Huxley</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>(HH), Morris-Lecar [6] and Leaky Integrate and Fire (LIF) [7] models
were used extensively here due to them being standard models in the
field of computational neuroscience. All share the feature that with
sufficient stimulation, these neurons produce voltage spikes, that
transmit onto other neurons via synapses whose strength dictates the
amount of stimulation neurons downstream of them experience. Neurons
with greater stimulation have a higher chance of themselves firing.
Neurons that provide positive stimulus to neurons downstream of it are
are known as excitatory neurons, and unless stated otherwise, all
neurons going forward should be assumed as such.</p>
<p>Following the work of Lindner and Schimansky-Geier [8], it was found
that stimulating certain neurons with a Gaussian noise-voltage waveform
of a particular optimum amplitude produced the strongest periodicity in
the emitted spike timings of the neuron. This is known as Coherence
Resonance (CR) and is explained by Lindner as the intensity of noise
enhancing the excitability of the neuron, as higher intensities
increases the probability for a transient voltage being sufficiently
high to illicit a spike. Too little amplitude and the chance of the
noise producing enough voltage for the neuron to fire is unlikely. Too
much noise amplitude and the neuron fires too often and stochastically.
This forms the basis of the related phenomena known as Stochastic
Resonance (SR), where in certain systems there exists an ideal amount of
noise that maximises the correlation between upstream and downstream
neurons spiking. This is important because spikes encode information in
an snn so this corresponds to maximising the distance information
encoded with spikes, can travel through the network. This motivated the
use of some form of intrinsic noise inside of the SNN architecture by
encoding intensities of input image data with frequency modulation, but
instead of a deterministic frequency, spikes occurred randomly being
Poisson distributed about the interval between a deterministic frequency
signal. Instead of explicitly computing the optimum amount of noise
(prohibitively expensive for large networks), the intensity of the noise
was increased by shifting the entire frequency modulation range up by
5Hz any time fewer than 5 neurons in the network spiked during a
training example [9]. An analytical treatment of CR and SR is provided
in their original paper [8] for a noisy excitable FitzHugh-Nagumo type
neuron system. This project primarily deals in demonstrating CR on the
simplified Leaky Integrate Fire model [7] (the neuron used in the SNN
section) for computational efficiency. Additionally Bio-plausible
deterministic yet chaotic sources of pseudorandom aperiodic drive were
also demonstrated using a ring of three coupled oscillators, made out of
Morris-Lecar style neurons.</p>
<p>Device-level and simulation-level work on memristive synaptic
circuits [10] in the literature describes AIST-type threshold memristors
as two-terminal resistive devices that are plausible candidates for
artificial STDP synapses [11]. Their conductance depends on non-volatile
(persistent even ages, 𝑉set or equivalently 𝑉+ Only when the voltage
applied across the terminals exceeds either threshold, there is a change
of opposing sign in the 𝑇, and 𝑉reset or equivalently 𝑉−𝑇. when powered
off) internal state variables that evolve under electrical stimulation.
They possess two suprathreshold volt­</p>
<disp-quote>
  <p>observed conductance of the memristor. Zhang et. al specifies an
  explicit voltage threshold model to explain the empirical findings of
  a fabricated AIST memristor by Y li et al. [10]. This group also
  reproduced STDP directly on the fabricated memristor, agreeing with
  STDP on average with non negli­gible stochasticity for any isolated
  update. This forms the backbone of the pulse programming scheme
  described in the memristor STDP synapse section.</p>
  <p>Finally, the STDP LIF SNN section based its work on that done by
  Diehl and Cook in 2015 [9]. They were the first to demonstrate, using
  pure unmodified STDP, higher accuracy than older approaches with
  simplified STDP rule proxies. Crucially, this architecture was fully
  unsupervised, marking a genuine milestone in neuromorphic machine
  learning.</p>
  <p>This project computationally simulated the AIST memristor to
  investigate the claim that it can act as an artificial STDP synapse to
  support learning inside of an SNN. The project also assessed the claim
  that the STDP rule was sufficient to perform unsupervised learning on
  an SNN.</p>
  <p>This paper is structured as follows: Firstly STDP is defined,
  moving on to the memristor simulation model used, where pulse
  programming and STDP is reproduced. Following that, an exploration of
  legacy biological neuron models that can both oscillate and fire only
  when sufficiently externally stimu­lated, are explored. These models
  explain the simplifications made in the more contemporarily relevant
  LIF non-oscillatory neuron model used in the SNN section. Then CR was
  inves­tigated on an LIF neuron, with a brief explanation of SR followed
  by simulating three neuron ring oscillators using Morris-Lecar
  neurons, to produce aperiodic and synchronised oscillations between
  them. Finally the STDP SNN section is presented, incorporating all
  sections before it: STDP synapses, LIF Neurons and SR. 100-, 400- and
  1600-neuron SNNs were trained and evaluated. Network specific
  mechanisms such as sparsity and homeostasis were also introduced, and
  explored. These findings are discussed in the broader context of
  memris­tor and neuromorphic literature, before the main conclusions and
  possible directions for future work are summarised.</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>II. Simulating STDP</p>
<disp-quote>
  <p>biological synapse). When Δ𝑡&gt; 0, the pre neuron fires before
  (LTP). This is interpreted as reinforcing synapses when the pre
  neurons activity stimulated and thus is a candidate for being (Δ𝑡&lt;
  0), the synapse experiences what is called Long Term</p>
</disp-quote>
<table-wrap>
  <table>
    <colgroup>
      <col width="33%" />
      <col width="33%" />
      <col width="33%" />
    </colgroup>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th>Δ𝑤(Δ𝑡) =</th>
        <th><p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <p>{𝐴+
            exp(−<strike><underline>Δ𝑡</underline></strike>−𝐴−exp(<strike>Δ𝑡𝜏−</strike>)
            for Δ𝑡&lt; 0<strike><underline>𝜏+</underline></strike>) for
            Δ𝑡&gt; 0</p>
          </disp-quote>
        </p></th>
        <th>(1)</th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
    </tbody>
  </table>
</table-wrap>
<p>(<bold>biphasic</bold>) of opposite sign with a discontinuity at Δ𝑡=
0.</p>
<p>pairs while weakening anti-causal pairings. In this sense it provides
a task-agnostic mechanism by which temporally consistent spike
relationships may be reinforced over repeated stimulus presentations.
This is explored in the discussion.</p>
<disp-quote>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image1.png" />
</disp-quote>
<p>Fig. 1. Idealized Biphasic STDP curve showing LTP and LTD
regions.</p>
<p><italic>B. Memristor model</italic></p>
<p>The memristor that was investigated was modelled using the
voltage-controlled threshold formulation proposed by Zhang, Wang [11],
to fit empirically observed AIST memristor be­haviour by Li [11]. This
model introduces voltage thresholds, and defines suprathreshold
(exceeding either threshold) con­ductance change dynamics that taper as
either end of the range of conductances a given memristor chemistry can
possess, is approached, known as saturation. This model remains compact
enough for repeated device-level and network-level simulation, but omits
device stochasticity for simplicity.</p>
<p>a) <italic>Suprathreshold Voltages and the state variable:</italic>
On a microscopic level, the AIST memristor contains silver electrodes
for its two terminals, with a solid polycrys­talline Ag-In-Sb-Te
substrate sandwiched in the gap between ductances). 𝑅on = 10 Ω and 𝑅off
= 420 Ω correspond to the</p>
<table-wrap>
  <table>
    <colgroup>
      <col width="100%" />
    </colgroup>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th><p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <p>the overall resistance 𝑅 is given by the linear
            interpolation (2) where 𝑡 is a time variable (see next
            section).𝑅(𝑡) = 𝑅on(<strike>𝑤(𝑡)𝐷</strike>) + 𝑅off(1
            −<strike>𝑤(𝑡)𝐷</strike>). (2)𝑉+𝑇= 0.37 𝑉 the resistance
            changes in one direction (in­when the applied voltage is less
            than 𝑉−filamentary phase crystals start growing, reducing
            resistance 𝑇= −0.19 𝑉 more</p>
            <p>𝑖on are current parameters with units of A. These are all
            fitted 𝜇𝑣 is a mobility parameter with units of
            <strike>m2</strike> d𝑤d𝑡= 𝜇𝑣= 1.6 × 10−12, 𝑖on = 1, 𝑖off =
            10−5<strike>,</strike> 𝑖0 = 10−3 { 𝜇𝑣(𝑅on
            0𝜇𝑣(𝑅on𝐷)(𝐷)(𝑖(𝑡)𝑖(𝑡)−𝑖0)𝑓(𝑤(𝑡)) if 𝑣(𝑡) &gt; 𝑉+𝑖on)𝑓(𝑤(𝑡))
            if 𝑉−if 𝑣(𝑡) &lt; 𝑉−𝑇≤𝑣(𝑡) ≤𝑉+ <strike>s</strike>Ω. 𝑖0,
            𝑖off, and 𝑇,𝑇.𝑇, (3)</p>
            <p>interval 𝑉−device state remains unchanged, providing the
            non-volatile behaviour necessary for use in synaptic
            circuits. Positive and 𝑇≤𝑣(𝑡) ≤𝑉+𝑇 defines a dead zone in
            which the the symbols used. They shouldn’t be interpreted as
            corre­sponding directly to any specific microscopic
            phenomena. The</p>
            <p>negative suprathreshold voltages therefore drive the
            state in opposite directions, allowing independent
            directional control of the memristors resistance
            (memristance) during pulse pro­gramming. And will form the
            basis of producing Biphasic lobes in the memristor STDP
            section.</p>
            <p>𝑤= 0 and 𝑤= 𝐷, the state equation was multiplied by a
            𝑓(𝑤(𝑡)) = 1 −(2<strike>𝑤(𝑡)𝐷</strike> −1) 2𝑝, (4)</p>
            <p>and then substituting 𝑤 into (2), to get a final
            resistance because Zhang et. al uses memristance, however in
            the STDP memristor section, conductances will be used
            exclusively. Conductance is the reciprocal of
            resistance.</p>
          </disp-quote>
        </p></th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
    </tbody>
  </table>
</table-wrap>
<graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image6.png" />
<p><italic>C. Pulse Programming Results</italic></p>
<p>a) <italic>Pulse Programming:</italic>
In Fig. 2 the conductance is dictated by the slope of resistances 𝑅on
(shallower line) and 𝑅off (steeper line) are where the voltage exceeds
𝑉+ into a line that doesn’t intersect the origin, thus describing an
evolving conductance as suprathreshold memristance pro­𝑇 and 𝑉−𝑇, does
the curve evolve conductance and resistance. It’s only in the parts of
I-V sweep</p>
<p>gramming is happening. the top right curve demonstrates an increasing
conductance and therefore a decreasing resis­tance, which is associated
with filament formation. By the same argument the bottom left most non
origin intersecting segment of the I-V curve represents filament
dissolution, as the resistance is increasing. This paragraph assumes a
counter clockwise rotation around the curve.</p>
<disp-quote>
  <p>−0.02</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>−0.04
0.00<inline-graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image2.png" /></p>
<disp-quote>
  <p>0.04</p>
  <p>0.02</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>) A ( <italic>I</italic></p>
<disp-quote>
  <p>−0.4 −0.2 0.0 0.2 0.4</p>
</disp-quote>
<p><italic>V</italic> ( V )</p>
<p>a ±0.5 V sinusoid at 500 Hz integration timestep used was Δ𝑡= 0.1𝜇s,
with 𝑉+ the simulated 𝐼–𝑉 trajectory in amperes. The slope of the line
from the 𝑇= 0.37 V, and 𝑉−𝑇= −0.19 V thresholds. The solid black loop
is</p>
<p>changing internal state of the AIST memristor.</p>
<p>of the threshold memristor. The device is driven by a ±0.6 V,</p>
<p>the lower resistance 𝑅on = 10 Ω (see (2)). As a result the the square
wave). The converse is true during the negative edge of the square
voltage, where the opposite threshold is exceeded, resulting in an
increasing resistance approaching</p>
<p>𝑅off = 420 Ω. It is clear from the curves seen in Fig. 2, Fig. 4 the
filamentary phase saturation resistance 𝑅on. It is clear the (a)</p>
<disp-quote>
  <p>0.6</p>
</disp-quote>
<table-wrap>
  <table>
    <colgroup>
      <col width="50%" />
      <col width="50%" />
    </colgroup>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th><p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <p>0.4</p>
          </disp-quote>
        </p></th>
        <th><italic>V</italic> +</th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
    </tbody>
  </table>
</table-wrap>
<disp-quote>
  <p>0.2</p>
</disp-quote>
<table-wrap>
  <table>
    <colgroup>
      <col width="33%" />
      <col width="33%" />
      <col width="33%" />
    </colgroup>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th>)</th>
        <th rowspan="4"><p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <p>0.0</p>
          </disp-quote>
        </p></th>
        <th rowspan="5"><italic>V</italic>−</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>V</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>(</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th rowspan="2"><italic>V</italic></th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th><p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <p>−0.2</p>
          </disp-quote>
        </p></th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
    </tbody>
  </table>
</table-wrap>
<disp-quote>
  <p>−0.4</p>
  <p>−0.6</p>
  <p>(b)</p>
  <p>−10</p>
  <p>−15−5
  0<inline-graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image3.png" /></p>
  <p>15</p>
  <p>10</p>
  <p>5
  ) A m ( <italic>I</italic></p>
  <p>0.0 0.2 0.4 0.6 0.8 1.0 <italic>t</italic> ( m s )</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>𝑅on = 10Ω, 𝑅off = 420Ω, 𝑉+±0.6 V square wave at 2 kHz over 0–1 ms
using a fixed 0.1𝜇s integration 𝑇= 0.37 V, and 𝑉−𝑇= −0.19 V, driven by a
Fig. 3. Square-wave pulse programming exceeds the update thresholds
and</p>
<disp-quote>
  <p>1.0</p>
  <p>0.4</p>
  <p>0.2</p>
  <p>0.0<inline-graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image4.png" /></p>
  <p>0.8</p>
  <p>0.6
  <italic>wD</italic> ) S m ( <italic>G</italic>
  10</p>
  <p>5<inline-graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image5.png" /></p>
  <p>25</p>
  <p>20</p>
  <p>15</p>
  <p>0.0 0.2 0.4 0.6 0.8 1.0 <italic>t</italic> ( m s )
  conductance trajectory. Same pulse-programming run as Fig. 3, with 𝑅on
  = 10Ω, 𝑅off = 420Ω, 𝑉+ at 2 kHz. Solid black trace is the normalised
  state <strike>𝑤</strike>grey trace is conductance 𝐺= and the
  corresponding nonlinear change in 𝐺. proportion of the terminal gap
  occupied by the filamentary phase. dashed 𝑇= 0.37 V, and 𝑉−
  <strike>𝑀</strike> in mS. Note the stepwise updates in
  <strike>𝑤</strike> 𝑇= −0.19 V, and a ±0.6 V drive 𝐷, representing
  the</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>Fig. 4 normalises the internal state variable, showing the changes
that occur during supra-threshold parts of the stim­ulating square wave
changing the filament width and thus resistance. The slope of the
changing filaments begin to flatten as it approaches the bounded
switching limits. The nonlinearity and asymetry in the suprathreshold
memristance update explains the pinch seen on the left of the I-V
curve.</p>
<p><italic>D. Implementing STDP on a memristor Results</italic></p>
<p>suprathreshold voltages are exceeded. Thus the Δ𝑤 variable</p>
<p>described in the <italic>Model Agnostic Spike Kernel</italic> section
with 50 ms and 150 ms time constants for depolarisation and the
memristor according to 𝑉post −𝑉pre, known as diffusive</p>
<p>some small 𝛿𝑉, then the diffusive coupling voltage becomes the
voltages). Since The AIST memristor has |𝑉−</p>
<p>This also motivated the choice of using exponentials to define |𝑉+𝑇|
in order to make the potentiation 𝑇| &lt; |𝑉+𝑇|,</p>
<p>the kernel, since the duration of time for which the diffusive
overlap remains surpassing either threshold voltage is invari­ant if both
pre- and post- synaptic spikes are scaled by the ating Δ𝐺 across three
separate initial conductances, as the</p>
<p>The behaviour very close to |Δ𝑡| = 0 (&lt; 7ms) is the tran­preted as
the discontinuity at Δ𝑡= 0 defined in (1), but since</p>
<p>such discontinuities is un-physical, a sign transition occurs</p>
<disp-quote>
  <p>over a narrow range.</p>
</disp-quote>
<graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image7.png" />
<p>Fig. 5. Pre/post spike overlap converts spike timing into a memristor
pro­</p>
<p>coupling 𝑉Post −𝑉Pre. Note that the negative coefficient for 𝑉Pre has
allready</p>
<disp-quote>
  <p>LTP and LTD.</p>
</disp-quote>
<graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image8.png" />
<disp-quote>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image9.png" />
</disp-quote>
<graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image10.png" />
<disp-quote>
  <p><inline-graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image11.png" />
  <inline-graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image12.png" />
  <inline-graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image13.png" />
  <inline-graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image14.png" />
  <inline-graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image15.png" />
  <inline-graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image16.png" /></p>
</disp-quote>
<graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image17.png" />
<p>approximately exponential tails. AIST threshold-memristor model with
𝑅on = 10Ω, 𝑅off = 420Ω, 𝑉+𝑇= 0.37 V, and 𝑉−𝑇= −0.19 V, driven by a
pre/post</p>
<graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image24.png" />
<p>(the conductance band), has on the amplitude of Δ𝐺 and time while the
time constant described how quickly |Δ𝐺| decayed</p>
<p>transitionary points of the 𝐺0-centred STDP sweeps. Here,</p>
<p>a strong coordinate transform of 𝜏 or equivalently Δ𝑡. Fig. 9 shows
the linear fits of 𝜏+ &amp; 𝜏−. It give gradients of +2.055 ×very strong
with |𝑟| &gt; 0.99 in both cases. The small gradients</p>
<p>window function attenuated conductance updates as the device
approached either limiting state. This confirmed that the model
preserved bounded conductance while still permitting STDP-like
plasticity within the interior of the conductance band.</p>
<p>The same fitted-amplitude curve in Fig. 8 also quantified the usable
update scale. The largest conductance updates occurred around the middle
of the conductance band, where the attenuation from either boundary was
weakest. Using the full 2.381 to 100 mS conductance range, whose width
is 97.619 mS, the maximum fitted conductance update was 0.3296 mS,
corresponding to approximately 0.338% of the full conductance-band
width.</p>
<p>If attention is restricted to the broad central update region,
roughly 30 to 78 mS, whose width was about 48 mS, the same update
corresponded to approximately 0.687% of that effec­</p>
<disp-quote>
  <p>tive range. This sub-percent scale is consistent with multi-level
  memristive synapse simulations that assume hundreds of resolvable
  conductance states; for example, 256 states imply a characteristic
  update quantum of about 0.39% of the available range [12].</p>
</disp-quote>
<graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image18.png" />
<graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image19.png" />
<graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image20.png" />
<graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image21.png" />
<disp-quote>
  <p>tance in the single-pair regime. For each 𝐺0, Pearson’s 𝑟 is
  computed between |𝑟|, where 0 indicates a perfect linearised
  exponential. Open circles are the conductance-dependent drift.</p>
</disp-quote>
<graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image22.png" />
<graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image23.png" />
<table-wrap>
  <table>
    <colgroup>
      <col width="100%" />
    </colgroup>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th><p>are fitted independently to the positive and negative
        outer lobes of Δ𝐺(Δ𝑡) for 50 initial conductances 𝐺0 sampled
        over [1 denote the positive-lobe fit; open squares denote the
        negative-lobe fit. Note 𝑅off,</p>
        <p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <p>the suppression of |𝐴| (see (1)) near the conductance
            extremes.</p>
          </disp-quote>
        </p>
        <p><strike>|𝐴+−𝐴−|𝐴++𝐴−</strike> across the same 50-point
        initial conductance sweep.</p>
        <p>endpoints, but it remained small across the sweep (10−3
        order</p>
        <p>tentiation or depression. This balance was important
        because</p></th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
    </tbody>
  </table>
</table-wrap>
<p>a strong systematic bias in either direction would have made learning
unstable.</p>
<graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image25.png" />
<graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image26.png" />
<disp-quote>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image27.png" />
</disp-quote>
<graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image28.png" />
<p>a weak conductance dependence. Time constants 𝜏+ and 𝜏− are extracted
from omitted. Open circles denote 𝜏+; open squares denote 𝜏−. The fitted
values</p>
<disp-quote>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image29.png" />
</disp-quote>
<graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image30.png" />
<p>conductance range. From the same 50-sample STDP sweep, the plotted
metric while peaks indicate conductance regions where set/reset
nonlinearity breaks symmetry.</p>
<disp-quote>
  <p>III. anatomy of a Neuron</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>In the previous section, STDP was demonstrated on a memristor using a
<italic>Model Agnostic spike Kernel</italic> for pre- and post-neuron
spike voltage waveforms shown in Fig. 14, applied over a sweep of
discrete relative spike times. This section aims to motivate the usage
of Fig. 14, by investigating the qualitative shapes of the spikes
produced by various Dynamical Neuron models. By analysing the stability
of the stable points of a simplified 2D Dynamical Morris-Lecar Neuron,
these qualitative voltage waveform characteristics were demonstrated, to
justify Fig. 14. The main points demon­strated will be that neurons can
be assumed to be charge</p>
<disp-quote>
  <p>leaking capacitors (equivalent to RC circuits), and the firing of a
  neuron corresponds to a sudden discharging of this capacitor and a
  part of the energy inside of a chemical battery store. The stable
  points of these dynamical systems dictate that such spikes are
  triggered by the neuron’s capacitor voltage exceeding a threshold
  (suprathreshold voltage crossing). The accumulation of charge in a
  neuron that slowly leaks is known as leaky integration. The Leaky
  Integrate and Fire (LIF) neuron is then introduced, which simplifies
  such models by forgoing multidimensional dynamics and instead
  modelling each qualitative behavior of spiking neurons independently,
  switching between regimes when appropriate. Then CR is demonstrated on
  LIF neurons, discussing its implications for using stochasticity in
  the SNN section and aperiodic oscil­lators are shown as an alternative
  non-stochastic form of aperiodic drive.</p>
  <p>Neuron models span a broad range of abstraction. At one extreme are
  biophysically detailed models, such as Hodgkin–Huxley (HH) type
  formulations, which reproduce electrophys­iological behaviour with high
  fidelity but are comparatively costly to analyse and simulate. At the
  other extreme lies the artificial neurons which are modeled as simply
  the sum of a linear combination of scalar neuron values feeding into
  it in ANNs as described in the abstract. Between these ends sits the
  leaky integrate-and-fire (LIF) neuron, which retains much of the
  qualitative behaviour of biologically faithful neuron models while
  remaining relatively computationally efficient, and easy to implement
  in hardware. This balance made it a suitable candidate for the present
  work, where spike timing and synaptic interaction were of greater
  interest. However, starting with the detailed differential equation
  geometry that governs neurotransmitter and ionic channel kinetics, in
  more biologically accurate models, explains the pragmatic choices that
  inspire the LIF model.</p>
  <p>a) <italic>Conductance-based neuron background:</italic>
  A biological neuron is an electrically excitable cell that
  communicates by emitting short voltage pulses called spikes, with a
  peak amplitude referred to as an action potential. To understand how
  all of this arises, first consider that the ion permeable insulating
  lipid membrane of a neuron acts as the plates of a capacitor that
  contain gated holes, that form resistive ion flow channels between the
  conductive charged intracellular and extracellular solutions,
  providing a resistive charge leakage pathway. This reduces A neuron to
  a Capacitor Resistor circuit. A change in the balance of ions across
  the membrane therefore changes the membrane capacitor voltage. The
  charge imbalance between the solutions also forms a electro-chemical
  battery in series with these resistive ion channels.</p>
  <p>The HH model is the benchmark for the most biologically realistic
  mechanistic neuron model in neuroscience, given by (5) describing the
  specifics of this leaky capacitor behaviour, with the opening and
  closing of three primary ion channel gating proteins modelled as
  voltage dependent variable resis­tors.</p>
</disp-quote>
<graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image31.png" />
<table-wrap>
  <table>
    <colgroup>
      <col width="33%" />
      <col width="33%" />
      <col width="33%" />
    </colgroup>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th>𝐶m</th>
        <th><p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <p>d𝑉d𝑡= 𝑔Na𝑚3ℎ(𝐸Na −𝑉) + 𝑔K𝑛4(𝐸K −𝑉) +𝑔L(𝐸L −𝑉) + 𝐼ext.</p>
          </disp-quote>
        </p></th>
        <th>(5)</th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
    </tbody>
  </table>
</table-wrap>
<p>with a membrane voltage 𝑉, with several proteins that gate</p>
<p>ions flowing into the cell via sodium channels which are</p>
<p>out of the potassium channels, gated by a third 𝑛 type protein.</p>
<p>channel sites.</p>
<table-wrap>
  <table>
    <colgroup>
      <col width="100%" />
    </colgroup>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th><p>dictated by the concentrations of the ions in and around
        the</p>
        <p>cell.</p>
        <p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <p>Each gate variable evolves according to a first-order
            equa­</p>
            <p>where 𝑥∈{𝑚, ℎ, 𝑛} and 𝛼𝑥(𝑉) and 𝛽𝑥(𝑉) are the voltage-d𝑡=
            <strike>𝑥∞(𝑉) −𝑥</strike>= 𝛼𝑥(𝑉)(1 −𝑥) −𝛽𝑥(𝑉)𝑥, (6)</p>
          </disp-quote>
        </p>
        <p>tion of the form</p>
        <p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <p>𝑥∞(𝑉) =𝛼𝑥(𝑉) + 𝛽𝑥(𝑉).𝛼𝑥(𝑉) (7)</p>
          </disp-quote>
        </p>
        <p>toward the steady-state equilibrium</p></th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
    </tbody>
  </table>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap>
  <table>
    <colgroup>
      <col width="100%" />
    </colgroup>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th><p>𝑚∞(𝑉), ℎ≈1, since empirically 𝑚 reaches equilibrium</p>
        <p>phenomenological Eyring-type exponential law [13], [14]
        in</p>
        <p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <p>The opening and closing rates were approximated by a</p>
            <p>𝐶d𝑉 <strike>d𝑛d𝑡</strike>= <strike>𝑛∞(𝑉) −𝑛</strike> d𝑡=
            𝐼in + 𝐼out + 𝐼ext = 𝑔Na𝑚∞(𝑉)(𝐸Na −𝑉) +<underline>𝑔K𝑛(𝐸K
            −</underline>𝑉) + 𝑔L(𝐸L −𝑉) + 𝐼ext, = 𝛼𝑛(𝑉)(1 −𝑛) −𝛽𝑛(𝑉)𝑛.
            (8) (9) Lecar model:</p>
          </disp-quote>
        </p>
        <p>the gate closing 𝛽𝑛, opening 𝛼𝑛 transition rates
        exponential</p>
        <p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <p>curves of <strike>𝑑𝑉</strike>gives
            <strike>𝑑𝑛</strike></p>
            <p>its equivalent hyperbolic-tangent form.</p>
            <p>where 𝑉𝑛 is a chosen parameter that gives 𝑛∞(𝑉𝑛)
            =<strike>1</strike></p>
            <p>By inferring the expression for 𝑛∞(𝑉) from (7) ,
            substi­</p>
            <p>The right-hand side is a logistic sigmoid, written here
            in 𝑛=
            𝑑𝑉= 0 when both curves intersect, producing a stable</p>
            <p><strike>𝛼𝑛(𝑉) + 𝛽𝑛(𝑉)</strike>= <strike>1</strike>
            𝑑𝑡= 0 and 𝑑𝑛</p>
            <p>𝛽𝑛(𝑉) = 𝐴𝑛exp(−𝑉−𝑉𝑛𝛼𝑛(𝑉) = 𝐴𝑛exp(<strike>𝑉−𝑉𝑛</strike>
            <strike>𝑑𝑡</strike>= 0 (the n and V nullclines). This</p>
            <p><strike>d𝑡</strike>= 0, (9) produces the
            <underline>𝑛</underline>-nullcline: 2(1 +
            tanh(<strike>𝑉−𝑉𝑛</strike> 𝑘𝑛𝑘𝑛 ), ), )). (11) (10) 2.</p>
            <p>𝑛 yields: Setting d𝑉</p>
            <p>In the following section the flow of 𝑛 w.r.t 𝑉 given by
            the 𝑛= 𝐼ext + 𝑔L(𝐸L −𝑉) + 𝑔Na𝑚∞(𝑉)(𝐸Na −𝑉) d𝑡= 0 in (8)
            gives the 𝑉-nullcline. Solving for</p>
            <p>𝑔k(𝑉−𝐸K) . (12) <italic>A. Monostable Dynamical Neuron
            Results</italic></p>
          </disp-quote>
        </p></th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
    </tbody>
  </table>
</table-wrap>
<disp-quote>
  <p>Depending on the set parameters, the nullclines describe different
  neuron types. The two that will be the focus of this</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>known as the excitable regime. Since 𝑛 evolves more slowly</p>
<graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image37.png" />
<p>faces is modelled by transient voltage perturbations from the resting
state.</p>
<disp-quote>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image32.png" />
</disp-quote>
<graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image33.png" />
<p>34.5𝜇 A/cm2, 𝑔𝐾= 8.0 mS/cm2, 𝐸𝐾= −84.0 mV, 𝑔Na = 4.4 mS/cm2, 𝐸Na =
120.0 mV, 𝑔𝐿= 2.0 mS/cm2, 𝐸𝐿= −60.0 mV, 𝜏𝑛= 10.0 ms. acts to set a
firing threshold voltage. If the perturbation remains on the resting
potential side of this separatrix, the trajectory decays back to it. The
accumulation of subsequent transient voltage perturbations, that slowly
decay back to the resting potential is known as leaky integration. If
the ampli­tude and frequency of these perturbations are sufficient to
cross the separatrix, the trajectory cannot return directly via the
decay path and instead makes a large excursion through phase space,
which can be seen in the yellow sample trajectory in Fig. 12. The
trajectory flows to the right and up, where voltage rise rapidly past
the threshold voltage, first arriving at the action potential. This step
is called depolarisation, and is the initial voltage rise seen in Fig.
13. The trajectory then traverses up and then left very quickly,
reducing the voltage to an overshoot potential, in a process known as
repolarisation. The slower outward recovery current pulls the trajectory
back down to the resting potential, known as hyperpolarisation. This
part of the trajectory hugs the much slower V null-cline, and thus
hyperpolarisation is always slower than re- and de- polarisation. Note
that any perturbation during the large voltage excursion, doesn’t
meaningfully change the qualitative behaviour of the trajectory until
the resting potential is reached again. This can be seen from the flow
lines where all excursion trajectories flow alongside each other towards
rest. This makes the duration of spiking, a refractory period, where
excitations can’t prematurely trigger another action potential, before
the resting potential is returned to first. Such a spiking regime is</p>
<disp-quote>
  <p>known as burst firing and Neurons that are current biased to behave
  like this are known as monostable neurons.</p>
</disp-quote>
<graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image34.png" />
<graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image35.png" />
<disp-quote>
  <p>Fig. 13. In the excitable regime, only suprathreshold perturbations
  trigger a full spike-and-recovery excursion. Voltage time series are
  shown for initial conditions chosen relative to the phase-plane
  threshold boundary. Light grey traces show subthreshold trajectories
  that return to rest; the solid black trace is a suprathreshold
  excursion producing a typical biological neuron spike kernel.</p>
  <p><italic>B. Model Agnostic Spike Kernel</italic></p>
  <p>The spike waveform shown in Fig. 14 was modelled by a piecewise
  exponent kernel intended to approximate and capture the qualitative
  regions found in the voltage spikes</p>
  <p>decay back to the resting potential 𝑉rest (not to be confused with
  the time translation 𝑡−𝜏.</p>
</disp-quote>
<graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image36.png" />
<p>to build pre/post waveforms for the STDP sweeps, with 𝜏spike = 50 ms
and 𝜏tail = 150 ms. Solid black curve is the kernel voltage; dashed and
dotted horizontal guides indicate the memristor thresholds 𝑉+ = 0.37 V
and 𝑉−=</p>
<p><italic>C. The LIF Model</italic></p>
<p>The preceding sections introduced mechanistic conductance gated
models for the membrane voltage, of a continuous dy­namical system
neuron. Leaky integration, threshold potential spiking and Spike kernels
were established. In this section the multidimensional dynamical systems
seen prior will be reduced to produce a monostable neuron, known as the
Leaky Integrate and Fire (LIF) model first introduced in 1907 by Lapique
[7].</p>
<disp-quote>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image38.png" />
</disp-quote>
<p>Fig. 15. The LIF circuit reduces membrane dynamics to leakage,
capaci­</p>
<table-wrap>
  <table>
    <colgroup>
      <col width="100%" />
    </colgroup>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th><p>represented by an input current 𝐼in(𝑡) corresponding to
        𝐼ext in (5) &amp; (8). Let 𝑉(𝑡) be the membrane voltage relative
        to the resting potential 𝑉rest. Current conservation gives</p>
        <p>the passive membrane equation becomes</p>
        <p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <p>Using Ohm’s law and capacitor voltage charge equation,
            𝐼in(𝑡) = 𝐼𝑅(𝑡) + 𝐼𝐶(𝑡). (13)</p>
          </disp-quote>
        </p>
        <p>can instead be written as
        Multiplying by 𝑅𝑚 and defining 𝜏𝑚= 𝑅𝑚𝐶𝑚 gives</p>
        <p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <p>If the input is written as an effective drive
            voltage,</p>
            <p>then</p>
            <p>For a conductance-based synaptic input, the input current
            𝜏𝑚</p>
            <p>𝜏𝑚
            𝐼in(𝑡) = 𝑉(𝑡) −𝑉rest</p>
          </disp-quote>
        </p>
        <p><strike>𝑑𝑉𝑑𝑡</strike>= 𝑉rest −𝑉(𝑡) + 𝑅𝑚𝐼in(𝑡).</p>
        <p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <p>𝑑𝑉𝑑𝑡= 𝑉rest −𝑉(𝑡) + 𝑉drive(𝑡). 𝑉drive(𝑡) = 𝑅𝑚𝐼in(𝑡),
            + 𝐶𝑚𝑑𝑉𝑑𝑡(14)</p>
          </disp-quote>
        </p>
        <p>(15)</p>
        <p>(16)</p>
        <p>(17)</p>
        <p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <p>Substituting this into the LIF equation gives</p>
            <p>𝜏𝑚𝑑𝑉𝑑𝑡= 𝑉rest −𝑉(𝑡) + 𝑅𝑚𝑔syn(𝑡)(𝐸syn −𝑉(𝑡)). (19) 𝐼syn(𝑡)
            = 𝑔syn(𝑡)(𝐸syn −𝑉(𝑡)). (18)</p>
          </disp-quote>
        </p></th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
    </tbody>
  </table>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap>
  <table>
    <colgroup>
      <col width="100%" />
    </colgroup>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th><p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <p>this becomes</p>
            <p>𝜏𝑚𝑑𝑉𝑑𝑡= −(𝑉(𝑡) −𝑉rest) + 𝑞(𝑡)(𝐸syn −𝑉(𝑡)). 𝑞(𝑡) =
            𝑅𝑚𝑔syn(𝑡), (20)</p>
            <p>(21) Defining the dimensionless conductance drive</p>
          </disp-quote>
        </p>
        <p>the passive membrane decay pathway corresponding to 𝑔𝐿 in</p>
        <p>stimulation, decaying back to the resting potential. Only
        this</p>
        <p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <p>Leaky Integration phenomena is being modelled by
            (15).</p>
            <p>b) <italic>Threshold Firing and reset:</italic></p>
            <p>To extend and include the qualitative spiking behaviour
            of</p>
            <p>𝑆[𝑡] = {1 if 𝑉[𝑡] ≥𝑉thr + 𝜃[𝑡] otherwise (22)</p>
            <p>neurons, the LIF neuron models a binary event
            variable</p>
            <p>event (𝑉&gt; 𝑉thr + 𝜃[𝑡]) occurs at time 𝑡, a spike is
            recorded at voltage 𝑉rst:𝑉[𝑡] →𝑉[𝑡] −𝑆[𝑡]𝑉rst. (23)</p>
          </disp-quote>
        </p>
        <p>potential. It is often set to 𝑉thr or just below to
        simulate</p>
        <p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <p>𝑛, 𝑛+ 1 is𝜃[𝑡𝑛+ 1] = 𝜆𝜃(𝜃[𝑡𝑛] + 𝑆[𝑡𝑛]), (24)</p>
          </disp-quote>
        </p>
        <p>dominating the competitive network. In hardware, again 𝜃</p>
        <p>voltage compared to the Membrane capacitor, feeding into</p>
        <p>the circuit block responsible for classifying a
        suprathreshold</p>
        <p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <p>crossing event.</p>
            <p>c) <italic>spike shaping:</italic></p>
            <p>Spike times are recorded, but to produce an actual
            spike</p>
          </disp-quote>
        </p>
        <p>kernel, LIF is optionally extended with an external pulse</p>
        <p>shaping circuit where the spike kernel is free to be
        chosen,</p>
        <p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <p>such as Fig. 14 used in the memristor STDP section.</p>
          </disp-quote>
        </p>
        <p>synaptic neuron so the input current to post synaptic neuron
        𝑖</p>
        <p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <p>𝐼in[𝑡] = ∑𝑤𝑖𝑗𝑥𝑗[𝑡], (25)</p>
          </disp-quote>
        </p></th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
    </tbody>
  </table>
</table-wrap>
<graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image43.png" />
<table-wrap>
  <table>
    <colgroup>
      <col width="20%" />
      <col width="20%" />
      <col width="20%" />
      <col width="20%" />
      <col width="20%" />
    </colgroup>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th rowspan="5">synaptic neuron i and the pre synaptic neurons
        j. 𝑥𝑗[𝑡] is the</th>
        <th rowspan="5">(a)</th>
        <th rowspan="2"><italic>m</italic></th>
        <th>0</th>
        <th rowspan="5"><p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image39.png" />
          </disp-quote>
        </p></th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>−20</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th rowspan="3"><italic>V</italic></th>
        <th>−40</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>−60</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>−80</th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
    </tbody>
  </table>
</table-wrap>
<disp-quote>
  <p>In this section Coherence Resonance in the LIF neuron is</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>demonstrated motivating the use of Poisson spike encoding</p>
<p>centered around 0V of intensity 𝜎. For each 𝜎, 12 independent</p>
<p>This produces a decaying random walk of the LIF Mem­𝐶ISI = Var(ISI)
(26) (ISI) variance (see Fig. 16):</p>
<p>Lecar, The LIF parameters used were: 𝑉rest = −65 mV, −50 mV, 𝜏𝑚= 20
ms (note this eliminates the need to spec­ify 𝑅𝑚, 𝐶𝑚 explicitly, with a
current density being sufficient for any 𝑅 in the system, see (15)),
integration step Δ𝑡= 0.1 ms, and constant subthreshold drive 𝑉in = 13.7
mV [6]. this is added to 𝑉rest in (15), eliminating the need to specify
−51.3 mV, just below the −50mV firing threshold potential,</p>
<p><italic>E. Coherence Resonance Results</italic></p>
<disp-quote>
  <p>e covariance</p>
</disp-quote>
<table-wrap>
  <table>
    <colgroup>
      <col width="25%" />
      <col width="25%" />
      <col width="25%" />
      <col width="25%" />
    </colgroup>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th rowspan="5">(b)</th>
        <th rowspan="2"><italic>m</italic></th>
        <th>0</th>
        <th rowspan="5"><p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image40.png" />
          </disp-quote>
        </p></th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>−20</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th rowspan="3"><italic>V</italic></th>
        <th>−40</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>−60</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>−80</th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <td rowspan="5">(c)</td>
        <td rowspan="2"><p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <p><italic>m</italic></p>
          </disp-quote>
        </p></td>
        <td>0</td>
        <td rowspan="5"><p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image41.png" />
          </disp-quote>
        </p></td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>−20</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td rowspan="3"><italic>V</italic></td>
        <td>−40</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>−60</td>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <td>−80</td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>
</table-wrap>
<p>the sweep: 𝜎low = 0.150 mV, 𝜎∗= 0.665 mV, and 𝜎high = 2.044 mV.
Spike</p>
<p>Any deviation from 𝜎∗ in either direction vastly increases the</p>
<table-wrap>
  <table>
    <colgroup>
      <col width="33%" />
      <col width="33%" />
      <col width="33%" />
    </colgroup>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th><p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <p>0.6</p>
          </disp-quote>
        </p></th>
        <th rowspan="2"><italic>σ</italic></th>
        <th rowspan="2">*
        trace uses vertical ticks to mark the detected spike times.
        These ticks should not be interpreted as a separate
        physical</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th><p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <p>0.5</p>
          </disp-quote>
        </p></th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
    </tbody>
  </table>
</table-wrap>
<table-wrap>
  <table>
    <colgroup>
      <col width="50%" />
      <col width="50%" />
    </colgroup>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th>I S I <italic>C</italic></th>
        <th><p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <p>0.4</p>
          </disp-quote>
        </p></th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
    </tbody>
  </table>
</table-wrap>
<disp-quote>
  <p>0.3</p>
  <p>0.2</p>
</disp-quote>
<table-wrap>
  <table>
    <colgroup>
      <col width="11%" />
      <col width="11%" />
      <col width="11%" />
      <col width="11%" />
      <col width="11%" />
      <col width="11%" />
      <col width="11%" />
      <col width="11%" />
      <col width="11%" />
    </colgroup>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th rowspan="3">I</th>
        <th>1.0</th>
        <th rowspan="7" colspan="7"><p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image42.png" />
          </disp-quote>
        </p></th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>0.8</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th rowspan="2">0.6</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>S</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th rowspan="5">I <italic>P</italic></th>
        <th>0.4</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>0.2</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th rowspan="3">0.0</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th><p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <p>0.0</p>
          </disp-quote>
        </p></th>
        <th>0.5</th>
        <th>1.0</th>
        <th><p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <p>1.5</p>
          </disp-quote>
        </p></th>
        <th>2.0</th>
        <th>2.5</th>
        <th>3.0</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th colspan="3"><italic>σ</italic></th>
        <th colspan="4"><p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <p>( m V )</p>
          </disp-quote>
        </p></th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
    </tbody>
  </table>
</table-wrap>
<p>neuron, and the mean normalised ISI covariance 𝐶ISI = Var(ISI)
∗⟨ISI⟩−2 is to reach 𝑃ISI = 1</p>
<disp-quote>
  <p>most regular spacing between events. Too little 𝜎 amplitude is much
  noise is shown in c) where the random walk exceeds the firing
  threshold too often and thus the stochastic nature of the noise signal
  shows up as highly aperiodic spike timings with a high inter spike
  time variance.</p>
  <p>This forms the basis of the related phenomena known as Stochastic
  Resonance (SR), where in certain systems there exists an ideal amount
  of noise that maximises the correlation between upstream and
  downstream neurons spiking. This corresponds to maximising the
  distance spikes and therefore information, can travel through the SNN.
  CR demonstrates that noise minimises the variance in the firing of an
  LIF Neuron. The lower the stochasticity of the firing of a neuron, the
  more different it appears to downstream neurons that otherwise are
  themselves stimulated by ambient stochastic</p>
</disp-quote>
<graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image47.png" />
<p>noise. This means a lower 𝐶ISI corresponds to a higher chance
<italic>F. Oscillators and Aperiodic Spike Circuits</italic></p>
<p>Having an aperiodic form of stimulation whether stochastic or
otherwise is useful for Stochastic Resonance. This is explored further
in the discussion section. Here, an aperiodic</p>
<p>nodes with membrane voltages Φ𝑖, where 1 drives 2, 2 drives 3 and 3
drives 1, each with directional conductances 𝑔12, 𝑔23 and 𝑔31,
respectively [6]. By specifying particular parameters</p>
<p>Central Pattern Generator (CPG). CPGs are often found in the motor
cortex of animals for autonomic nervous system functions that require
rhythmic alternating motions such as breathing, and walking. Self
sustained spiking is called tonic</p>
<p>is increased, the 𝑉 nullcline in Fig. 19 is translated upwards there
is only one point of intersection between the nullclines. This is how
the same model can describe both monostable neurons and also produce
oscillator neurons, furthering the idea that such multidimensional
dynamical models encode a large number of important distinct qualitative
features in a very compact yet computationally expensive way.</p>
<table-wrap>
  <table>
    <colgroup>
      <col width="17%" />
      <col width="17%" />
      <col width="17%" />
      <col width="17%" />
      <col width="17%" />
      <col width="17%" />
    </colgroup>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th rowspan="2">ϕ</th>
        <th><p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <p><italic>g</italic> 12</p>
          </disp-quote>
        </p></th>
        <th rowspan="2">ϕ</th>
        <th rowspan="2"><p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <p>2</p>
          </disp-quote>
        </p></th>
        <th><italic>g</italic> 23</th>
        <th rowspan="2"><p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <p>3</p>
          </disp-quote>
        </p></th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th><p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <p>1</p>
          </disp-quote>
        </p></th>
        <th>ϕ</th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
    </tbody>
  </table>
</table-wrap>
<p><italic>g</italic> 3 1</p>
<p>Fig. 18. A three-neuron ring circuit provides a minimal directionally
coupled oscillator network. Each neuron projects forward to the next
neuron in a closed loop, so activity circulates around the ring rather
than terminating at a feedforward output layer. The directed coupling
defines the firing order and supports phase-structured dynamics,
including synchronised circulation, stable phase offsets, and aperiodic
timing structure in the oscillator simula­tions. The couplings are
excitatory.</p>
<disp-quote>
  <p><italic>G. Oscillator and Aperiodic Spike Circuit
  Results</italic></p>
  <p>Fig. 19 shows the post SNIC bifurcation flow diagram of</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>the dynamical system just like in Fig. 19, where the saddle and</p>
<p>stable nodes got closer together till they meet and annihilate</p>
<p>leaving just one unstable node remaining, as denoted by the</p>
<p>intersection point of both nullclines. Once this happens, there</p>
<p>is no longer a stable resting state to trap the dynamics, and the</p>
<p>trajectory instead evolves onto a stable limit cycle, producing</p>
<p>repetitive oscillatory spiking as can be seen in the membrane</p>
<p>voltage time evolution in Fig. 20. These limit cycles possess</p>
<p>basins of stability, as seen in the flow, where all trajectories</p>
<disp-quote>
  <p>approach the limit cycle, in the long term.</p>
</disp-quote>
<p><inline-graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image44.png" />Tonic
cycle</p>
<disp-quote>
  <p>0.2</p>
  <p>0.1</p>
  <p>0.0<inline-graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image45.png" /></p>
  <p>0.4</p>
  <p>0.3</p>
  <p><italic>n</italic> ) V m ( <italic>V</italic>
  −60 −40−20 0 20 40 60 Fig. 19. Increasing bias current from 35mA/cm2
  in Fig. 12 to 47mA/cm2 shown in the monostable nullcline in Fig. 12
  showing a post-SNIC bifurcation</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>oscillatory regime. Note that now there is only one unstable point of
inter­</p>
<p>section between the nullclines. The flow paths of non limit cycle
trajectories</p>
<disp-quote>
  <p>also corroborates the persistent limit cycle.</p>
  <p>−20</p>
  <p>−40</p>
  <p>−60<inline-graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image46.png" /></p>
  <p>60</p>
  <p>40</p>
  <p>20</p>
  <p>0</p>
  <p>0 25 50 75 100 125 150 175</p>
</disp-quote>
<p><italic>t</italic> ( m s )</p>
<p>Fig. 20. Post-SNIC bias produces tonic spiking with a locked
constant</p>
<p>interspike period. Voltage time series in the oscillatory regime show
repeated</p>
<p>frequency 𝜔= 0.550349<strike>rad</strike> The following parameters
produced synchronized oscilla­s.</p>
<p>spikes after transient decay. The absence of convergence to a resting
potential</p>
<p>and the near-regular repetition are consistent with a stable limit
cycle with</p>
<p>tions Fig. 21, with stable 2<strike>𝜋3</strike> phase offsets and a
1–2–</p>
<table-wrap>
  <table>
    <colgroup>
      <col width="50%" />
      <col width="50%" />
    </colgroup>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th colspan="2"><p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <p>10.0𝜇𝐴/cm−2 (for all i), 𝜔ref = 0.550349 rad/ms (the base
            shows the expected <underline>𝜑1</underline>2 =
            2<strike>𝜋3</strike>, 𝜑13=
            <underline>4</underline><strike>𝜋<underline>3</underline></strike>.
            φ₃</p>
          </disp-quote>
        </p>
        <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image48.png" /></th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
      <tr>
        <td>spikes</td>
        <td><inline-graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image49.png" /></td>
      </tr>
    </tbody>
  </table>
</table-wrap>
<disp-quote>
  <p>φ₁</p>
</disp-quote>
<table-wrap>
  <table>
    <colgroup>
      <col width="100%" />
    </colgroup>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th>Fig. 21. Identical Morris-Lecar neuron oscillators provide a
        120° CPG Lecar limit cycle and repeated with phase offsets 𝜑= 0,
        𝜑= 2<strike>𝜋</strike>4<strike>𝜋3</strike>. This is the
        zero-detuning reference condition. 𝐼𝑖<underline>=
        10</underline>𝜇A/c<strike>m</strike>2 <strike>3</strike>, and
        𝜑=</th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
    </tbody>
  </table>
</table-wrap>
<disp-quote>
  <graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image50.png" />
</disp-quote>
<table-wrap>
  <table>
    <colgroup>
      <col width="50%" />
      <col width="50%" />
    </colgroup>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th><p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <p>spikes</p>
          </disp-quote>
        </p></th>
        <th><inline-graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image51.png" /></th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
    </tbody>
  </table>
</table-wrap>
<disp-quote>
  <p>φ₁
  φ₂
  φ₃</p>
  <p>(8, 10, 14)(𝜇A/cm2). and coupling constants 𝑔= 0.005 mS. The
  repeated identified as (𝐼1, 𝐼2, 𝐼3) = (8, 10, 14)(𝜇A/cm2), with the
  frequencies are sufficiently different and the coupling strength is
  too weak to produce synchrony. Fig. 23 corroborates the expectation
  that the phases diverge monotonically. This is</p>
  <p>further seen in the voltage waveform Fig. 22, where the firing
  phase and order appear chaotic. Simulation times of 4700 ms and 1000
  ms are shown respectively to highlight that this aperiodicity isn’t
  just a transient behaviour before the system settles to synchrony.</p>
</disp-quote>
<graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image52.png" />
<graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image53.png" />
<graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image54.png" />
<disp-quote>
  <p>Fig. 23. Unwrapped phase differences drift approximately linearly,
  confirming absence of stable phase locking. Same three-neuron network
  as Fig. 22; phases are extracted from late-time voltages and
  differences are unwrapped. Both differences continue to increase
  without settling, which is direct evi­dence of persistent phase
  drift.</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>IV. Feed-Forward STDP SNN</p>
<disp-quote>
  <p>The previous sections introduced the concept of an STDP synapse,
  Then AIST memristors were shown to reproduce this rule well, when
  spike shaped LIF neurons were applied across it with a diffusive
  coupling voltage.</p>
  <p>The LIF neuron was also introduced and investigated in­cluding under
  stochastic stimulation. This section focusses on highlighting the
  value of reproducing STDP, with its impli­cations for training SNNs
  being explored. The LIF Neuron, STDP model and Poisson based
  stochastic aperiodic drive will be incorporated into an SNN trained to
  recognise handwritten digits. Some new network level ideas will be
  introduced, such as homeostasis mechanisms which act to prevent a
  subset of neurons from firing too often, and sparsity, which is any
  mechanism that promotes a network to store learned repre­sentations of
  training data on as few synapses in the network as possible. This
  maximises representational efficiency given a finite number of
  synapses in an SNN.</p>
  <p>a) <italic>Synaptic Plasticity Update:</italic>
  The symmetric biphasic STDP (1) rule was used
  b) <italic>Network Dynamics and Synaptic Integration:</italic>
  Uptill this point only excitatory coupling between neurons have been
  considered, where the pre-synaptic Neuron drives the post synaptic
  neuron, increasing its stimulation and thus its chance of firing. To
  implement a functional competitive in the network, The architecture
  relies on the interplay between excitatory (E) neurons and inhibitory
  (I) neurons. These Neurons actively discharge the membrane capacitors
  of the post synaptic neurons they feed into, reducing their chance of
  firing. Thus the LIF model used is identical to (21) with the addition
  of k inhibitory and j excitatory pre synaptic neurons feeding into a
  post synaptic neuron i:</p>
  <p>As before 𝜏 represents the membrane time constant, which 𝜏𝑉𝑖=
  (𝐸rest −𝑉𝑖) + ∑𝑔𝐼𝑖𝑘(𝐸inh−𝑉𝑖)𝑔𝐸𝑖𝑗(𝐸exc−𝑉𝑖) + (27)</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>channel conductance (𝑔𝑒jump followed by an exponential decay:</p>
<disp-quote>
  <p>where 𝑔𝑖𝑘 &amp; 𝑔𝑖𝑗 are the learned conductances using the with
  𝑔𝐸𝜏𝑔𝑒𝑔𝐸𝑖𝑗= −𝑔𝐸𝑖𝑗(𝑡= 0) = 𝑔𝑖𝑗, 𝑔𝐼 𝑖𝑗 and 𝑔𝑖and 𝑖𝑘) undergoes an
  instantaneous 𝜏𝑔𝑖𝑖𝑘(𝑡= 0) = 𝑔𝑖𝑘,𝑔𝐼𝑖𝑘= −𝑔𝐼 (28)</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>non zero synaptic conductance 𝑔𝑥𝑦 from pre x to post y be equivalent
to the LIF STDP memristor synapse, the spike kernel needs to contain an
exponential voltage rather than a fixed gate potential seen in LIF and
Morris Lecar Neuron models. This is another motivation behind using
exponential in their reversal potentials. While 𝐸exc drives 𝑉post
upward, Consequently, the driving force (𝐸inh −𝑉𝑖) is strongly
neg­excitation, when inhibitory Neurons fire they accelerate the removal
of charge from the membrane capacitor of the post-synaptic neuron,
discharging it at a rate exceeding its passive leakage.</p>
<p>c) <italic>Training Data:</italic>
Input images were 28*28 monochrome images of a curated set of 420000
human handwriting examples of the digits 1 to 9, by the Modified
National Institute of Standards and Tech­</p>
<p>maximum pixel intensity, out of 255 equally spaced possible
intensities, was divided by 4 and converted into frequencies,</p>
<p>sity encoded into a frequency. If fewer than five spikes were emitted
by the entire excitatory population of the SNN during presentation of a
particular example, the maximum input rate was increased 5Hz and the
same image was presented again until sufficient activity had been
elicited. This harks back to</p>
<p>the adaptive Poisson frequency range as a variable 𝜎 proxy.</p>
<disp-quote>
  <p>Between successive images, a 150 ms interval with no input in Fig.
  24. The first was an input layer of 28 × 28 = 784 excitatory layer.
  All input pixel spike trains were fed into every Excitatory neuron,
  with STDP synapses in between. The pattern of input pixels to which a
  particular excitatory neuron has become most sensitive is known as the
  receptive input pixel can be visualised like a 28 ∗28 MNIST image.
  exitatory neuron from the previous layer that drives it with a fixed
  non trainable synapse. Every Inhibitory neuron connects backwards
  all-to-all except to that the neuron driving it in the excitatory
  layer.</p>
</disp-quote>
<graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image55.png" />
<disp-quote>
  <p>learning. Pixel intensities from a 28 × 28 MNIST image are
  converted to projects back to all excitatory neurons except its source
  neuron, creating lateral inhibition and a soft winner-take-all
  dynamic.</p>
  <p><italic>A. Competition and Homeostasis</italic></p>
  <p>a) <italic>Lateral Inhibition:</italic>
  Competition is a type of sparsity mechanism. Neurons react to inputs
  and compete, with whichever neuron emitting the most charge, having
  its synapse strengthened more than others reacting to the same thing.
  It was implemented on the excita­tory neurons through a dedicated
  inhibitory population, using the connectivity shown in Fig. 24. Each
  excitatory neuron projected to exactly one inhibitory neuron, and each
  inhibitory neuron projected back to all excitatory neurons except the
  one from which it received input. This connectivity created lateral
  inhibition and hence a soft winner-take-all dynamic. The</p>
</disp-quote>
<graphic mimetype="image" mime-subtype="png" xlink:href="vertopal_eeafef3e038144a7a1457352de4d5cea/media/image56.png" />
<p>strongest neuron most strongly inhibited all others. Because it
reacted most strongly, the lateral inhibition it experiences is also
less than what all other excitatory neurons experience. This made it
more likely that only a small subset of excitatory neurons reacts most
strongly to a given training example, thus promoting sparse
representations in the excitatory neurons. as Poisson spike rates so a
larger excitatory 𝜏 allows the information across multiple images
providing more stable learning, whilst inhibition can still act quickly
on a single training example providing a per image winner neuron. this
forces the inhibitory neurons to only provide competition, and does not
meaningfully participate in building a rich learnt representation of the
training data.</p>
<p>b) <italic>Adaptive Thresholding:</italic>
To prevent a small subset of excitatory neurons from dominating the
response, the network also implemented a homoeostasis mechanism through
an adaptive threshold. This was identical to that described in equation
(24). A neuron that had recently been highly active becomes temporarily
harder to excite, redistributing competition across the population and
encouraging receptive fields to differentiate, and to get excitatory
neurons to detect different digits from one another.</p>
<p><italic>B. Training</italic></p>
<p>Training was unsupervised. Synaptic weights were learned from
presentations of the MNIST training set without class labels. Labels
were introduced only after learning had fin­ished. At that stage,
learning was disabled, neuron thresholds were fixed, and each excitatory
neuron was assigned to the digit class for which it showed the highest
average response over the training set. During evaluation, the predicted
digit was taken to be the class whose assigned neurons exhibited the
highest mean firing response. No separate classifier was placed on top
of the spiking network. An Nvidia RTX 4090 graphics processing unit
(GPU) was used to simulate networks with 100, 400, and 1600 excitatory
neurons.</p>
<p>run reaches a final training-window accuracy of 74.8% after 40000
images, the 𝑁= 400 run reaches 94.4% after 180000 Fig. 26 shows a clear
population-size effect. The 𝑁= 100 <italic>C. Training
results</italic></p>
<disp-quote>
  <p>level result in the simulation set: the architecture does not only
  fit its training-window metric, but retains substantially improved
  performance on the test data. For this graph, the 400 neuron result
  was omitted because the simulation crashed before those figures could
  be obtained.</p>
</disp-quote>
<table-wrap>
  <table>
    <colgroup>
      <col width="20%" />
      <col width="20%" />
      <col width="20%" />
      <col width="20%" />
      <col width="20%" />
    </colgroup>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th rowspan="3">)</th>
        <th>100</th>
        <th rowspan="10" colspan="3"><p specific-use="wrapper">
          <table-wrap>
            <table>
              <colgroup>
                <col width="10%" />
                <col width="10%" />
                <col width="10%" />
                <col width="10%" />
                <col width="10%" />
                <col width="10%" />
                <col width="10%" />
                <col width="10%" />
                <col width="10%" />
                <col width="10%" />
              </colgroup>
              <thead>
                <tr>
                  <th rowspan="2" colspan="2"></th>
                  <th rowspan="2" colspan="3">79</th>
                  <th></th>
                  <th></th>
                  <th>93</th>
                  <th colspan="2"><p specific-use="wrapper">
                    <disp-quote>
                      <p>.5</p>
                    </disp-quote>
                  </p></th>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <th><p specific-use="wrapper">
                    <disp-quote>
                      <p>.4</p>
                    </disp-quote>
                  </p></th>
                  <th></th>
                  <th></th>
                  <th></th>
                  <th></th>
                </tr>
              </thead>
              <tbody>
                <tr>
                  <td colspan="2"></td>
                  <td colspan="2"></td>
                  <td></td>
                  <td></td>
                  <td></td>
                  <td></td>
                  <td></td>
                  <td></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td colspan="2"></td>
                  <td colspan="2"></td>
                  <td></td>
                  <td></td>
                  <td></td>
                  <td></td>
                  <td></td>
                  <td></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td></td>
                  <td>3</td>
                  <td colspan="2"><p specific-use="wrapper">
                    <disp-quote>
                      <p>.9</p>
                    </disp-quote>
                  </p></td>
                  <td rowspan="2"></td>
                  <td rowspan="2"></td>
                  <td rowspan="2"></td>
                  <td rowspan="2"></td>
                  <td rowspan="2"></td>
                  <td rowspan="2"></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td></td>
                  <td></td>
                  <td></td>
                  <td></td>
                </tr>
                <tr>
                  <td></td>
                  <td></td>
                  <td></td>
                  <td></td>
                  <td></td>
                  <td></td>
                  <td></td>
                  <td></td>
                  <td></td>
                  <td></td>
                </tr>
              </tbody>
            </table>
          </table-wrap>
        </p></th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>80</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th rowspan="2">60</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>%</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>(</th>
        <th rowspan="4">40</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>t</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>e t</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th rowspan="4"><italic>A</italic></th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>20</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th rowspan="2">0</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th><italic>N</italic>=2 5</th>
        <th><italic>N</italic>=1 0 0</th>
        <th><italic>N</italic>=1 6 0 0</th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
    </tbody>
  </table>
</table-wrap>
<p>size simulations with 𝑁= 25, 𝑁= 100, and 𝑁= 1600 excitatory
neurons;</p>
<disp-quote>
  <p>The confusion matrix in Fig. 27 shows where the remaining errors
  occur. Highest probability (yellow colour intensity) lies on the
  diagonal, confirming that the output assignment rule 93.55%, giving a
  7% error rate and agrees with the repeated-rather than as a fully
  optimised state of the art classifier, and there are certainly many
  ANNs that can outperform it (Gradient Descent exceeds 99% accuracy as
  noted by Diehl &amp; Cook [9]).</p>
  <p>100</p>
  <p>90</p>
  <p>80</p>
  <p>) % ( <italic>A</italic>
  70</p>
  <p>60</p>
  <p>50</p>
</disp-quote>
<table-wrap>
  <table>
    <colgroup>
      <col width="9%" />
      <col width="9%" />
      <col width="9%" />
      <col width="9%" />
      <col width="9%" />
      <col width="9%" />
      <col width="9%" />
      <col width="9%" />
      <col width="9%" />
      <col width="9%" />
      <col width="9%" />
    </colgroup>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th rowspan="5">the high-accuracy regime, consistent with the
        original Diehl–Cook observation that larger excitatory
        populations provide</th>
        <th rowspan="5">40</th>
        <th rowspan="5"><p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <p>0</p>
          </disp-quote>
        </p></th>
        <th rowspan="5">100</th>
        <th rowspan="5"><italic>n</italic> t r a i n</th>
        <th rowspan="4">200</th>
        <th rowspan="5"><p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <p>i m a g e s )</p>
          </disp-quote>
        </p></th>
        <th rowspan="5"><p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <p>300</p>
          </disp-quote>
        </p></th>
        <th><italic>N</italic></th>
        <th>=</th>
        <th><p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <p>1 0 0</p>
          </disp-quote>
        </p></th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th><italic>N</italic></th>
        <th>=</th>
        <th><p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <p>4 0 0</p>
          </disp-quote>
        </p></th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th><italic>N</italic></th>
        <th>=</th>
        <th rowspan="3"><p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <p>1 6 0 0</p>
          </disp-quote>
        </p></th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th rowspan="2" colspan="2">400</th>
      </tr>
      <tr>
        <th>( 1 0 3</th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
    </tbody>
  </table>
</table-wrap>
<p>from 𝑁= 100 to 𝑁= 1600 raises the mean test accuracy</p>
<p>1600 excitatory neurons using seed 42. Line styles distinguish
network size 74.8%, 94.4%, and 98.0% respectively.</p>
<p>V. discussion</p>
<p><italic>A. Device-Level Plasticity</italic></p>
<p>Initially the STDP rule (1) was defined. STDP can be explained as
promoting meaningful computations to take place in an SNN without
explicitly defining an algorithm to solve a particular task. Computation
in an SNN occurs by manip­ulating the time distribution of spikes as they
travel through the network, from input sensory neurons to output action
neurons. When some meaningful coordinated computation is being done by
some neurons, then it may be expected that a group of connected neurons
will fire close together in time, in the order of the feed forward
excitatory influence they have been arranged in. This way LTP reinforces
any task agnostic, well coordinated computations that may randomly arise
in the SNN when sensory input is fed in. The idea is that applying STDP
after every exposure to many different training examples for a
particular task, only the subset of well coordi­nated computations
actually relevant to solving the training task, gets reinforced,
potentiating the same synaptic pathways consistently. IN contrast,
chance based correlations found in noise or unrelated parts of the
training data, change which synapses get strengthened every new training
example. Thus these irrelevant yet well coordinated computations average
out to contribute very little to the overall synaptic structure of the
network. What is left may be thought of as groups of neurons forming
specialised circuits that perform some task relevant computations that
feed into each other to give the desired output. LTD is there to weaken
synapses that may happen to exist between a pair of neurons that have
settled into different independent specialised circuits. Due to this,
Spikes produced before the upstream neuron, producing Δ𝑡&lt; 0 (the
condition</p>
<p>feed into one post synaptic neuron (via a distinct synapse for each
pre-synaptic neuron). A larger time gap between a pre and post neuron
spiking has a larger chance that a different other pre neuron caused the
superthreshold voltage crossing that triggered the firing of the post
synaptic neuron. This LTD also decays when |Δ𝑡| →∞. between an AIST
memristor and an STDP-like synapse. The The first part of the project
established the physical link ambiguity increases with time so it is
sensible for LTP to decay with spike timing separation. By the same
argument,</p>
<p>AIST model in Fig. 2 and the pulse-programming response in Fig. 3 and
Fig. 4 show the same central mechanism of device conductance evolving
with the time integral of a non linear suprathreshold update function
(3) when driven by either a positive or negative suprathreshold voltage.
This corresponds to the formation and dissolution of a lower resistance
fila­mentary phase in the crystal structure of the AIST substrate. The
resistance of such a device depends on its own recent programming
history, with a bounded resistance caused by the</p>
<p>persist, making its conductance 𝐺 suitable for storing synaptic</p>
<disp-quote>
  <p>tive spike timing into a suprathreshold pulse duration, signed
  opposingly between causal and anti causal firing cases. In Fig. 6,
  causal timing produced LTP and anti-causal timing</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>changed about |Δ𝑡| = 0. This is why the fits in Fig. 8, Fig. 7,</p>
<p>sign is still correct, so although synaptic updates may not be in
Fig. 8, 1 −𝑒−<strike>7</strike> is lost by having this cusp region. This
is not Ideal for use in 65 ≈10% of the overall Ideal STDP strength as
strong near zero, the correct type of update still happens. Compared to
the approximately 65 ms time constants found</p>
<disp-quote>
  <p>The Δ𝐺 amplitude also falls to zero near the conductance SNN for
  example. Over the region where the amplitude is the highest and the
  flattest (30 to 78 mS) the update amplitude percentage is 0.6% of this
  window which falls in line with estimates made by Kim et. al [12], for
  sufficient amplitude ratios needed for effectively training an SNN
  using the STDP rule. All in all this strongly supports the use of such
  AIST memristors as STDP synapses, fulfilling the first aim of this
  project. Although there is the caveat from the 10% cusp atten­uation
  from the previous paragraph that needs to considered. Also the device
  model used did not take into account any de­vice stochasticity and
  device-to-device variability that matters in a fabricated SNN array,
  that affect STDP reproducibility. Approaches such as active spike
  amplitude normalisation, batch together many synapses and re-normalise
  the action potentials of neurons explicitly to stabilise the synaptic
  update amplitude to be more consistent across the conductance range,
  and to artificially shrink the cusp region. These form a good passage
  for further exploration.</p>
  <p>Then the groundwork for the SNN section was laid with the LIF
  neuron being derived from more complicated dynamical neuron models, by
  replicating threshold firing and Laaky inte­gration dynamics of
  biological ion channels. Then followed</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>particular level of gaussian noise amplitude 𝜎∗= 0.665mV.</p>
<p>SNN architecture. Other Network mechanisms such as lateral inhibition
and adaptive thresholding was used to implement competition and
homeostasis respectively.</p>
<p>CR demonstrates that noise increases the excitability of the LIF
neuron, so it is easier for a neuron to transmit information to
downstream. This is of course also true for just reducing the firing
threshold voltage of LIF neurons, but that would also make the SNN less
tolerant of external noise. It is by the fact that Gaussian noise is
Aperiodic and centered on 0V, that on average the overall increase in
the excitability of the neuron is 0. Adding an aperiodic background
drive means that connected chains of neurons will only occasionally have
a transient boost in the excitability of the downstream neuron favoring
the chance that a coincidental upstream neuron firing will trigger a
cascade of downstream neurons to fire. Since STDP strengthens synapses
when downstream neurons fire shortly after upstream neurons, it
asymmetrically favors and strengthens the stimulation the upstream
neuron has on the downstream neuron. In the case where the transient
gaussian noise voltage waveform made the downstream neuron harder to
fire (by being negative), there is a lower chance that the pre synaptic
neuron causes the post neuron to have a suprathreshold voltage crossing
event to begin with, reducing the chance for there being a spike pair
for STDP to react to. this way STDP asymmetrically favours aperiodic
voltage sources superimposed into the membrane voltages of spiking
neurons in SNNs, increasing the distance information can travel in the
network, whilst maintaining its original noise tolerance. Using
randomness to achieve this is known as Sto­chastic Resonance (SR). This
motivated investigating aperiod Chaotic biologically plausible
oscillators presented in its own section, and the use of Poisson
distributed sensory neuron stimulus in the Diehl Cook SNN.</p>
<p>The Diehl–Cook unsupervised SNN reproduction combined the preceding
pieces into an explicit network-level test of whether the local STDP
rule could facilitate unsupervised learning. The architecture in Fig. 25
highlights a crucial mechanism. All input pixels project to all
excitatory neurons, each excitatory neuron projects to one of its own
inhibitory neuron, and inhibitory feeds backwards suppresses every other
competing excitatory neurons in the SNN. This is known as Lateral
inhibition and creates a soft winner-take-all mechanism. When one neuron
responds strongly to an input digit, lateral inhibition prevents all
neighbouring neurons from learning the same pattern at the same time,
thus making learned representations to be more efficiently stored on a
minimal number of synapse weights. STDP then strengthens the weights
between the poisson coded active input pixel neurons and the winning
neuron, making the neuron more selective for that feature in future
presentations. Homeosta­sis is a complementary mechanism. The adaptive
threshold described in the LIF section makes recently active excitatory
neurons temporarily harder to activate, so competition does not collapse
onto the first few neurons that happen to react strongly to something.
This allows for more training examples to have a chance to influence the
learned features, without the SNN getting too hung up on some
correlation that may occur in early examples that might have just been
noise. This</p>
<p>explains why the receptive fields of each neuron specialises for a
specific digit and in Fig. 29 and Fig. 30 appear to visually encode the
average of many different common hand­writing variations, demonstrating
the ability of the network to learn the general concepts behind the
features present in te training data, without the use of any image
labels, or given any external feedback on how accurate its predictions
were. Despite this, the SNN failed on around 7% of examples on average
with the final tested accuracy being 98%. In summary lateral inhibition
strengthens transient correlations found in the most recent training
examples, while homeostasis slowly redistributes the incremental
knowledge gained each training example, whilst protecting previously
learned knowledge from being overwritten by strong transient updates.
This pairing is why the network resembles vector quantisation or
self-organ­ising maps seen in traditional ANNs that require expensive
synchronised global weight matrix updates. The accuracy results are
strong in the broader context of Neuromorphic racies of 82.9%, 87.0%,
91.9%, and 95.0% for 𝑁 = 100,</p>
<disp-quote>
  <p>in Fig. 27, which is within margin of error of the original
  author’s results. Note that the 6400 neuron simulation was not
  reproduced due to restricted funding for compute resources compared to
  the Authors. The confusion matrix in Fig. 28 and the a sample of the
  SNN’s failures in Fig. 31 show its limita­tions. Ambiguous handwritten
  examples can still activate the wrong assigned population. Such
  failure modes are expected from a shallow unsupervised architecture,
  since it learns useful stroke and digit templates, but it does not
  have the hierarchical abstraction of more layered networks, that allow
  them to abstract and handle ambiguity better. Diehl and Cook make the
  same broader comparison in their benchmark table, where supervised or
  less biologically constrained systems performed worse, but state of
  the art conventional Gradient Descent methods can reach higher
  accuracies (99%). Diehl &amp; Cook’s work remain valuable because of
  its simplicity, unsupervised nature and class leading performance
  amongst biologically inspired synaptic update/ learning rules. Aside
  from some ANNs getting higher accuracies, the 98% peak accuracy
  obtained still strongly supports the conclusion that STDP is
  sufficient to perform very well as a training rule for an SNN,
  answering the second aim of this project. Further work could involve
  modifying STDP to perform even better, to try and reach parity with
  ANNs and to investigate ways in which much larger SNNs with more
  neuron layers can be implemented.</p>
  <p><italic>B. Overall Assessment</italic></p>
  <p>Taken together, the results support the project aim: a compact
  AIST-style memristor model can reproduce a local, timing-dependent
  conductance update, and a Diehl–Cook style STDP SNN can learn
  recognisable MNIST structure with strong accuracy. The strongest
  conceptual chain is that pulse timing becomes AIST memristor
  conductance updates, memristor conductance updates mimics the STDP
  synaptic</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>plasticity rule in an SNN, lateral inhibition turns plasticity into
competition inside of an SNN, and homeostasis prevents competition from
degenerating into a few neurons monopolis­ing SNN behaivour. This chain
gives a coherent neuromorphic story from device physics to network
function, motivated by the energy efficiency of neuromorphic systems
seen in the literature.</p>
<p>The main caveat is that the results in this paper do not directly
demonstrate the hardware efficiency that motivates neuromorphic
computing. Training was slow and inefficient because event-driven STDP
still had to be simulated sequen­tially on conventional synchronous
hardware. A physical memristor crossbar, by contrast, would update many
synapses asynchronously in parallel through local device physics, which
is the reason memristive synapses and spiking neuromorphic hardware
remain attractive. Existing neuromorphic processors already show the
appeal of this direction: TrueNorth demon­strated large-scale spiking
networks performing tasks success­fully at milliwatt power levels [21],
with Loihi demonstrating similar energy gains on programmable Spiking
Neural archi­tecture [22]. No power measurement was performed in this
project, so those references should be treated as motivation rather than
evidence in favour of the presented SNN compared to traditional
ANNs.</p>
<p>VI. Conclusion</p>
<p>This project demonstrated a coherent simulation pathway from
device-level memristor dynamics to network-level un­supervised learning.
The AIST threshold-memristor model reproduced the core ingredients
required for a synaptic device: non-volatile state-dependent
conductance, threshold-ed pulse programming, bounded saturation, and
polarity-dependent set/ reset behaviour. When driven by overlapping pre-
and postsy­naptic spike kernels, the model produced a biphasic STDP-like
conductance update, with causal timing producing LTP and anti-causal
timing producing LTD. The fitted outer lobes were approximately
exponential across the usable conductance range, while the update
amplitude correctly fell toward zero near the conductance limits. The
conductance update was weak when the spike timing magnitude fell below
7ms, and the lack of control in the strength of the updates is a
drawback of using AIST memristors as STDP synapses. Further work could
explore the many ways these drawbacks are overcome by supplementing AIST
memristors with additional circuitry. Overall this still supports the
use of AIST memristors for STDP synapses well and shows promise, thus
the first aim of the project was successful.</p>
<p>The neuron-model simulations helped justify the abstrac­tions used in
the network section. Conductance-based and reduced phase-plane models
showed how threshold crossing and spike generation arise from continuous
membrane dynam­ics, while the LIF coherence-resonance simulations showed
that noise can improve spike-timing regularity at an interme­diate noise
strength. The oscillator and ring-circuit simulations further
illustrated how structured or aperiodic timing sources could be used to
as a pseudorandom noise source.</p>
<disp-quote>
  <p>At network scale, the reproduced Diehl–Cook style archi­tecture
  showed strong unsupervised learning behaviour [9]. Lateral inhibition
  created competition between excitatory neurons, while adaptive
  thresholds provided homeostasis so</p>
  <p>93.544% mean test accuracy. This result compares favourably
  formance whilst being unsupervised. For example The work done by
  Hussain et al. [23] just a year before, using the super­vised
  Morphology rule only achieved an accuracy of 90.3% [9]. The use of
  STDP in this SNN provides an elusive pathway to implement such devices
  with memristive STDP synapses providing low energy spike circuits and
  asynchronous local plasticity, where autonomous synaptic strength
  updates occur naturally from device physics, allowing for massively
  parallel computation at a per synapse level. The two aims of the
  project are therefore complementary, as the AIST memristor provides a
  very compact STDP synapse implementation (the terminal gap is just
  3nm), providing a proof of concept to im­plementing low energy
  artificial STDP synapses in hardware, and the STDP SNN gives STDP
  synapses a meaningful role in facilitating highly parallel
  asynchronised synaptic updates, that this SNN demands. Future work
  should therefore focus on moving beyond the concept level, and towards
  tackling the device non-idealities present in fabricated arrays,
  increasing the depth of the networks (currently there’s only 3 layers)
  and size of the networks, to be able to take on more difficult and
  practical real world machine learning tasks. Put together, the second
  aim of the project was also successfully carried out. All together
  both aims were thoroughly investigated, and plans for future work have
  been outlined.</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>VII. Acknowledgements:</p>
<disp-quote>
  <p>All reproduction graphs were reproduced independently by Tabeeb
  Rahman. Fig. 24 comes from [9].</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>References</p>
<table-wrap>
  <table>
    <colgroup>
      <col width="50%" />
      <col width="50%" />
    </colgroup>
    <thead>
      <tr>
        <th><p>[1]</p>
        <p>[2]</p>
        <p>[3]</p>
        <p>[4]</p>
        <p>[5]</p>
        <p>[6]</p></th>
        <th><p specific-use="wrapper">
          <disp-quote>
            <p>F. Rosenblatt, “The Perceptron: A Probabilistic Model for
            Information Storage and Organization in the<italic>gical
            Review</italic>, vol. 65, no. 6, pp. 386–408, 1958, doi:
            .</p>
            <p>B. Widrow and M. E. Hoff, “A Circuits,” <italic>1960 IRE
            WESCON Convention Record</italic>, vol. 4, pp. 96–104,
            1960.</p>
            <p>C. E. Shannon, “A Mathematical Theory of Communication,”
            <italic>The Bell</italic> no. 3, pp. 379–423, 1948, doi:
            .</p>
            <p>B. Landers, and H. Pinkard, “ARC-AGI-2: A New Challenge
            for Frontier AI Reasoning <italic>505.11831</italic>, 2025,
            [Online]. Available:
            anian, “Brain power,” <italic>Proceedings of the
            National</italic> l. 118, no. 32, p. e2107022118, 2021, doi:
            .</p>
            <p>“Voltage Oscillations in the Barnacle Giant Muscle Fib,
            no. 1, pp. 193–213, July 1981, doi: .</p>
          </disp-quote>
        </p></th>
      </tr>
    </thead>
    <tbody>
    </tbody>
  </table>
</table-wrap>
<p>[7] L. Lapicque, “Recherches quantitatives sur l'excitation
électrique des nerfs traitée comme une polarisation,” <italic>Journal de
Physiologie et de</italic> <italic>Pathologie Générale</italic>, vol. 9,
pp. 620–635, 1907.</p>
<p>[8] B. Lindner and L. Schimansky-Geier, “Analytical approach to the
stochastic FitzHugh-Nagumo system and coherence
resonanc<italic>­</italic> l. 60, no. 6, pp. 7270–7276, 1999, doi: .</p>
<p>[9] . Cook, “Unsupervised learning of digit recognition using
spike-timing-dependent plasticity<italic>onal</italic>
<italic>Neuroscience</italic>, vol. 9, p. 99, 2015, doi: .</p>
<p>[10] Y. Li <italic>et al.</italic>, “Activity-dependent synapnide
electronic synapse for neur<italic>Scientific Reports</italic>, vol. 4,
p. 4906, May 2014, doi: .</p>
<p>[11] Y. Zhang, X. Wang, Y. Li,an, “Memristive Model for Synaptic
Circuits,” <italic>IEEE Transactions on Circuits and</italic> vol. 64,
no. 7, pp. 1–5, 2017, doi: .</p>
<p>[12] iking Neural Network (SNN) With Memristor Synapses Having
Non-linear Weight Update,” <italic>Frontiers in­nce</italic>, vol. 15, p.
646125, 2021, doi: .</p>
<p>[13] ion channels: Past, present, and future,”
<italic>ysiology</italic>, vol. 144, no. 1, pp. 7–26, 2014, doi: .</p>
<p>[14] , T. Yamanishi, K. Ptak, M. Z. Mogri, and J. C.</p>
<disp-quote>
  <p>Smith, “Real-time kinetic modeling of voltage-gated ion channels
  using
  dyna<italic>rnal</italic>, vol. 95, no. 1, pp. 66–87, 2008,
  doi: .</p>
</disp-quote>
<p>[15] W. G<italic>iking Neuron Models: Single Neurons,</italic>
<italic>Populations, Plasticity</italic>. Cambridge: Cambridge
University Press, 2002. [16] W. Gerstner, W. M. Kistler, R. Naud, and L.
Paninski, <italic>Neuronal</italic> <italic>Dynamics: From Single
Neurons to Networks and Models of Cognition</italic>.</p>
<p>ity Press, 2014. [Online]. Available: /
[17] rges, “MNIST handwritten digit data­ base,” <italic>ATT Labs
[Online]. Available: http://yann.lecun.com/exdb/mnist</italic>, vol. 2,
2010.</p>
<p>[18] S. Song, K. D. Miller, and L. F. Abbott, “Competitive Hebbian
Learning through Spike-Timing-Dependent Synaptic <italic>ure
Neuroscience</italic>, vol. 3, no. 9, pp. 919–926, 2000, doi: .</p>
<p>[19] T. Masquelier and S. J. Thorpe, “Unsupervised Learnea­ tures
through Spike Timing Dependent Pl <italic>Biology</italic>, vol. 3, no.
2, p. e31, 2007, doi: . [20] T. Masquelier, R. Guyonneau, and S. J. T­
dent Plasticity Finds the Start of Repeating Patterns in Co
<italic>ONE</italic>, vol. 3, no. 1, p. e1377, 2008, doi: .</p>
<p>[21] A million spiking-neuron integrated circuit with a scalable
communication networ, vol. 345, no. 6197, pp. 668–673, 2014, doi: .</p>
<p>[22] M. Davies <italic>et al.</italic>, “Loihi: A NProcessor with
<italic>cro</italic>, vol. 38, no. 1, pp. 82–99, 2018, doi: .</p>
<p>[23] . Basu, “Improved Margin Multi-Class Classification Using
Dendritic Neurons with Morphological Learning,” in <italic>2014 IEEE
International Symposium on Circuits and Systems</italic> stralia: IEEE,
2014, pp. 2640–2643. doi: .</p>
</body>
<back>
</back>
</article>
